<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dialogues between Philerene and Philalethe, a lover of peace and a lover of truth, concerning the Pope's supremacy. Part I</title>
            <author>Watts, Thomas, 1665-1739.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65321</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27584</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09959972</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09959972</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44415</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65321)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44415)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1370:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dialogues between Philerene and Philalethe, a lover of peace and a lover of truth, concerning the Pope's supremacy. Part I</title>
                  <author>Watts, Thomas, 1665-1739.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Watts,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Thomas Watts.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popes --  Primacy.</term>
               <term>Popes --  Temporal power.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  France.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44415:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44415:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DIALOGUES BETWEEN <hi>Philerene</hi> and <hi>Philalethe,</hi> A Lover of PEACE, and a Lover of TRUTH; Concerning the POPE's SUPREMACY.</p>
            <p>PART I.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>IMPRIMATUR, Liber cui Titulus, [<hi>Dialogues between</hi> Philéréne <hi>and</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lalethe.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <date>
                              <hi>March</hi> 27. 1688.</date>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IL. NEEDHAM,</hi> R.R. in Chriſto P. ac D.D. <hi>Wilhelmo</hi> Archiep. <hi>Cant.</hi> a Sacr. Domeſt.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Watts,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard.</hi> 
               <abbr>MDCLXXXVIII</abbr>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:44415:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44415:2"/>
            <head>ADVICE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT is above a year ſince this little Treatiſe hath been fit for the Preſs; and if the Author had pleaſed he needed not have delayed the Publiſhing of it ſo long; but as he did not undertake it with that deſign, ſo he did not conſent to it, but at the ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a judicious and learned Friend, for whoſe Advice he had the ſame regard, as for his Commands.</p>
            <p>You will not find in theſe Diſcourſes that delicacy of Expreſſion, and that juſtneſs of Speech which are the ornament and beauty of the greateſt part of the works of this Age: For beſides that the ſtile of Dialogues ought to be plain and eaſie, the Author never made any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of that high-raiſed and lofty Eloquence, which, as a Learned Man of our Age ſays,<note n="*" place="margin">Monſieur <hi>Nicole</hi> dans l'art de penſer.</note> ſeduces men into error by its counterfeit ſplendor. He always thought that ſolid Eloquence conſiſted in Matter, and not in Words; and that it were incomparably better for a Man to ſay a great deal in few words,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Plutar. <hi>in</hi> Phoc.</note> than little or nothing at all in a great many. He ever eſteemed the Conciſeneſs of <hi>Cicero</hi> before the Copiouſneſs of <hi>Demoſthenes;</hi> and always held this maxim of the Fathers concerning Eloquence in Holy things, That the Eloquence of thoſe who make Religion their Subject, ought to conſiſt in the weight of their Matter, and of their Reaſon; and that they ought to explain themſelves after an eaſie manner, that all ſorts of people might under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them. <hi>When we ſpeak of God, ſays St.</hi> Cyprian,<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypr.</hi> ad Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum.</note> 
               <hi>the Diſcourſe we make uſe of to prove the Faith, ought not to depend upon the ſtrength of Eloquence, but of Matter. The Church,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi>
               <note n="*⁎*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Atha.</hi> Orat. de ſemente.</note> 
               <hi>is not a School of Sophiſters
<pb facs="tcp:44415:3"/>nor of Orators.</hi> And the famous St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> lib. 4. de doc. Chriſt. c. 15. &amp;c.</note> tho he were one of the moſt eloquent of his time, freely declares, <hi>That a Man were better be reproved by the Gramarians, than not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the people; and that a Preacher of the Goſpel ought chiefly to endeavour to make himſelf to be underſtood and heard with deſire, and with a ſpirit of ſubmiſſion, of his Audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; which he may better arrive to by the Piety of his Prayers, than by the Artifice of his Diſcourſe.</hi> If you take good heed, you ſhall find that falſe Teachers have always hid themſelves under the vail of falſe Eloquence<note n="†" place="margin">Vid. 1 Cor. 2. 1 Cor. 11.6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>, and that it is out of this Golden Cup that they have made men drink the mortal Poyſon of Error; whereas the Apoſtles and all Orthodox Teachers<note n="‖" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Irenae.</hi> lib. 1. Adverſ Haereſ. Valent. Orig. lib. 11. de principiis, &amp; lib. 4.5. contra Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum.</note> taking a contrary way, made it their glory to uſe a great ſimplicity of ſpeech, wanting that which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls the enticing words of mens wiſdom. The Author hath followed theſe noble and glorious methods, and without putting himſelf to the trouble of ending his Periods in their juſt meaſure (keeping however to the purity of the language, as much as poſſibly he could) he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied himſelf chiefly to the weight and force of his Reaſons. You will find in him, I hope, ſufficient to perſwade and to convince you, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided you bring with you an eaſie, peaceable, and wholly unprejudiced mind: This is the ſpirit that runs throughout this whole work; and it was this ſpirit that began and finiſhed the deſign, the Author ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not propoſed to himſelf any other aim than that of animating Chriſtians to the ſearching out of Peace and Truth, two the greateſt happineſſes that ever men can arrive to.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, If this little Treatiſe hath the good fortune to pleaſe, we may furniſh you with ſome others which the Author hath compoſed at more leaſure, and which he hath enriched with ſome particular ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations which he hath made, by Reading the moſt Ancient and the moſt Learned Fathers of the Church. Accept however of this, with the ſame mind that he offereth it to you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quod Glorioſus fratres quam ſubjici &amp; vinci a veritate: ſuperet te veritas volentem nam &amp; invitum ipſa ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abit.</hi> Aug. <hi>in</hi> Pſalm <hi>57.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogues">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44415:3"/>
            <head>DIALOGUES BETWEEN <hi>PHILERENE</hi> and <hi>PHILALETHE.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">PART I.</head>
            <div n="1" type="dialogue">
               <head>The Firſt Dialogue.</head>
               <p>NOtwithſtanding the Difference between <hi>Philalethe</hi> and <hi>Philéréne</hi> as to their Age, they were both of them perſons of ſo great Worth, and their Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations were ſo much alike, that ſcarce had they ſeen one another three or four times, but they contracted a very ſtrict Friendſhip.</p>
               <p>As they never were better pleaſed than when they were together, they oftentimes left their ordinary Employments, for the Satisfaction of ſeeing one another; and conferring together, as well concerning things which they had Read, as thoſe they had Heard of. In this Deſign they often went to walk upon a River-ſide, from whence they could diſcover one of the fineſt and richeſt Countries of all <hi>France.</hi> And as they were both of them men of great Learning, and of a clear Apprehenſion, they went always home greatly ſatisfied with their Converſation.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:44415:4"/>
               <p>They made uſe of the firſt fine days which the Spring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded, to renew their deſireable Converſation, which the ſeverity of the Winter had interrupted: And the firſt time they met, having given Aſſurances of their mutual Affection, and ſhewed how glad they were to meet in a place where they might freely diſcover their moſt ſecret. Thoughts to each other, <hi>Philéréne</hi> ſpoke thus to his Friend;</p>
               <p>Have you not heard talk, my dear <hi>Philalethe,</hi> of the preſent Affairs? I mean, of the Deliberation which the Aſſembly of the Clergy hath taken? I have, anſwered <hi>Philalethe,</hi> heard ſomething of it, but I cannot give you a full Account o'nt; if you know it, you will oblige me to tell it me.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philéréne.</speaker>
                  <p>I need not tell you, my dear Friend, that my Lords the Biſhops of <hi>Tournay,</hi> of <hi>Meaux,</hi> of St. <hi>Maloes,</hi> of <hi>Vaur,</hi> of <hi>Châalons,</hi> and of <hi>Aleth,</hi> had been named by the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the Clergy, to examin the Six Propoſitions of the <hi>Sorhonne,</hi> preſented to the King in 1663. becauſe you know it already. But what perhaps you do not know, is, That the Clergy did Aſſemble the <hi>17th.</hi> of the laſt Month, after the uſual manner, and took the Report of theſe Prelates. My Lord Biſhop of <hi>Tournay,</hi> who was Head of the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, began the Report, and delivered himſelf very Learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon this Occaſion. The next day in the Evening the other Commiſſioners were heard; and they diſcourſed upon this Subject with great Learning. The <hi>19th.</hi> in the Morning they ſpoke every man in this turn upon the Subject of their Commiſſion; and at Night, the Company being re-aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, they, by a general Conſent, approved of a Declaration, which contains theſe following Propoſitions.</p>
                  <p>The Firſt is, That neither the Pope, nor the Church it ſelf, hath any Power, directly nor indirectly, over the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porality of Kings; That they cannot be depoſed; and that their Subjects cannot be abſolved from their Oaths of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to them upon any account whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>The Second is, That the Council is above the Pope, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Doctrine eſtabliſhed in the <hi>14th.</hi> Seſſion of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44415:4"/>Council of <hi>Conſtance;</hi> which the Aſſembly declares to have had the full Power and Approbation of the Church.</p>
                  <p>The Third is, That the Uſe of the Pope's Power ought to be limited by the Canons, and that he can do nothing to the Prejudice of the Ancient Cuſtoms and Liberties of the <hi>Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane</hi> Church.</p>
                  <p>The Fourth is, That the Pope hath the Chief or Principal Authority in things which concern the Faith; but ſo, that his Deciſions are not certain without the Churches Conſent.</p>
                  <p>The Aſſembly ordered at the ſame time, That this Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſhould be written in <hi>Latine,</hi> and ſent to all the Prelates of <hi>France,</hi> to be Signed by them; and that the King ſhould be petitioned to make an Edict for the Execution of it through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Kingdom.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philalethe.</speaker>
                  <p>This is <hi>Brave,</hi> and looks like the Apoſtolical Vigour and Heroick Courage of our Ancient Prelates.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>This is not all. Theſe Lords Commiſſioners were diſpatched away to the King; and having given an exact Account of the Behaviour of the Clergy, they demanded an Edict in the Kings Name, for the Execution of their Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. His Majeſty granted them the Edict, which was made as followeth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And by this Edict the King ordains, That this Declaration ſhall be Regiſtred in all the Courts of Parliament of the Kingdom, and in all the Faculties of Divinity and of the Canon-Law: And his Majeſty doth Prohibit, under grievous Penalties, even Foreigners within his own Kingdom, and all, as well Seculars as Regulars, to teach any thing contrary to what is contained in this Declaration.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Edict hath been executed. The Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> hath Regiſtred this Declaration of the Clergy with that Zeal and Readineſs that cannot be too much commended, and which all other Parliaments of the Kingdom ought to imitate.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>It cannot be denied but that our Prince is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable in all his Actions; that <hi>France</hi> never ſaw upon the Throne a Monarch of ſo High a Character, and of ſo great a Power; that he maintains moſt worthily upon all occaſions, the Glorious Title of <hi>Lewis the Great,</hi> which his Heroick Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44415:5"/>have acquired him. And that the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> hath done well to expreſs the great Zeal which they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways had for the Rights of the Crown, and for the Liberty of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, againſt the Enterprizes of the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> You may have read in our Hiſtories what here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore <hi>Philip the Auguſt, Philip the Fair, Charles the 6th, 7th, and 8th, Lewis the 9th, 11th, and 12th</hi> did: You know alſo the Conduct of the ſame Parliament under all theſe Great Princes, to maintain according to their Will and Pleaſure the Rights of the Crown, and the Privileges of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church. And I believe alſo, that you have heard of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees which this Honourable Houſe hath ſent forth under <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>13th.</hi> againſt the Scandalous Books of <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>terel</hi> and of <hi>Bellarmin:</hi> But we may ſay without exceſs, That <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> in this Conjuncture, hath ſhewed more ſtedfaſtneſs and greatneſs of Mind, in the Oppoſition which he hath made againſt the Attempts of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> than all his Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Predeceſſors ever did. And it cannot alſo be denied, but that the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> hath gone on worthily in the Footſteps of their Glorious Anceſtors.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>It is not in this ſingle Affair only, that this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe of Parliament have ſhewed their Zeal to Second the Intentions of his Majeſty, and to maintain the Rights of the Crown, and the Privileges of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church: They have alſo given notable Proofs of it in the Affair of Father <hi>Buhi</hi> the <hi>Carmelite.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>I have alſo heard of a <hi>Theſis</hi> which this Father had maintained the <hi>4th.</hi> of <hi>December</hi> laſt; and it was ſaid, that they had cauſed him ſome Trouble about it at <hi>Rome;</hi> but I do not preciſely know, what were the Propoſitions which this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did maintain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>If my Memory doth not fail me, I think there were Six: The Firſt of them is, That there are ſome Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Laws to which the Pope himſelf is ſubject. The Second is, That he cannot upon all occaſions diſpence with the Canons of General Councils. The Third is, That he cannot Depoſe Kings, nor impoſe Tributes upon their Eſtates without their Conſent. The Fourth, That Biſhops hold their Juriſdiction from God. The Fifth, That the Faculty
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44415:5"/>of Divinity at <hi>Paris,</hi> doth not eſteem the Pope to be Infallible. And the Sixth, That the Right of the Regale is neither a Fancy nor an Uſurpation. Theſe Propoſitions greatly ſtirred up the Pope againſt this Father, he ordered the Commiſſary General of the <hi>Carmelites</hi> to declare him deprived of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges of his Order, and uncapable of performing any fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, either Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, or Preaching. This Command was ſent to the Superior of the <hi>Carmelites</hi> of the place <hi>Maubert</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">A Street in <hi>Paris</hi> ſo called.</note> to whom this Commiſſary General had given advice of the Noiſe that this Theſis of Father <hi>Buhi</hi> had made at <hi>Rome,</hi> and of the misfortune wherewith the whole Order was threatned. This Father demanded a Copy of the Letter of his Superior, that he might conſult his Friends about it, which was granted him; The Affair coming at length to the King's ear, there came forth a Letter under the Seal, to the Superior, forbidding him to execute any Order from <hi>Rome</hi> againſt Father <hi>Buhi,</hi> without the King's knowledg and conſent: Yet notwithſtanding this, the Superior cauſed the Order to be Regiſtred, which he had received from the Commiſſary General of the <hi>Carmelites</hi> the 18th of <hi>February</hi> laſt. But the Parliament ſhewed the ſame vigour in this Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair as in that of the Declaration of the Clergy; for after many proceedings made at the inſtance of the Attorny Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, the Parliament ordered that the Superior of the <hi>Carmelites</hi> ſhould be admoniſhed for his Diſobedience, and expreſly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad the execution of the Order againſt Father <hi>Foelix Buhi;</hi> to which they added, That he ſhould continue in his Function of Divinity Reader, expreſly forbidding any perſon to moleſt him; and at length they Order that the Commiſſary Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral's Letter ſhould be razed out of the Regiſter, and laid aſide: And this by order of Parliament, the 14th day of <hi>April</hi> 1682.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>The Parliament did very bravely in this Affair, and ſhewed that the ſame ſpirit of Zeal and Courage ſtill reigns in that Honourable Aſſembly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thilér.</speaker>
                  <p>But ought not we to fear that this ſhould cauſe ſome rupture with the Pope? Into what confuſion and diſorder might not ſo unfortunate an accident caſt us?<note n="†" place="margin">Greg. Naz. <hi>Orat. 12.</hi>
                     </note> Were we not better to Sacrifice ſomewhat to the good of our peace, which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44415:6"/>is the greateſt Legacy that our Saviour left to his Apoſtles,<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 14.27.</note> 
                     <hi>Pacem meam do vobis?</hi> What is there more precious than Union and Concord, ſince that Jeſus Chriſt gave ſo great a Character of it to his Diſciples?<note n="†" place="margin">Joh. 13.35.</note> 
                     <hi>In hoc cognoſcent omnes quia mei Diſcipuli eſtis ſi dilectionem habueritis ad invicem.</hi> What is there more prejudicial than diſunion and diſcord which deſtroy the moſt flouriſhing States? <hi>Omne regnum diviſum contra ſe deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labitur &amp; domus diviſa contra ſe non ſtabit.</hi> Matt. 12.25.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>I agree with you, that we ought to do our utmoſt to obtain Peace; that we ought to ſacrifice our own Intereſts; nay, that for ſo great a good we ought to relinquiſh things that ſeem to us of importance. <hi>Ipſum enim nomen pacis amabille,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Auſtin;</hi> but you muſt own too, that we ought to do nothing for Peace to the prejudice of Truth; St. <hi>Paul</hi> joyns theſe one with the other,<note n="‖" place="margin">Eph. 4.15.</note> 
                     <hi>Veritatem facientes in Charitate.</hi> And God, who calls himſelf Charity, calls himſelf alſo Truth; I know alſo that the Fathers of the Church exhort us greatly to avoid Schiſm as a mortal poiſon; but a Peace made againſt the intereſt of Truth, is not a real Peace; and when we cannot make it, and maintain it, but at the prejudice of this Trurh, it were better that a Scandal ſhould ariſe, than that Truth ſhould be abandoned. <hi>Satius eſt,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Bernard, ut ſcandalum oriatur quam ut veritas diſceratur.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>How! My dear <hi>Philal.</hi> Do you think that the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of the Clergies Declaration, and of Father <hi>Buhi</hi>'s The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, contain ſuch eſſential and ſuch important Truths, that it would be a crime not to defend them, tho it were to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance of the Publick Peace?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, Dear <hi>Sir,</hi> I am very well perſwaded that all theſe Propoſitions are founded upon Texts of Scripture, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Canons of Councils, and upon the perpetual and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Tradition of the Church, principally of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church; and by conſequence, I believe that we ought not to depart from them any ways, and that we cannot do it without danger: But becauſe it will be a matter of long Diſcourſe, I ſhall defer the examining of it to another walk.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:44415:6"/>
               <head>The Second Dialogue.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PHilalethe</hi> and <hi>Phileréné,</hi> who were no leſs deſirous to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain each other upon the ſubject whereon they had begun, than to enjoy the fine weather of the Spring, came the next day to the place appointed for their Converſation.</p>
               <p>Scarce had they walked a turn or two, talking of indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent matters, but <hi>Philalethe,</hi> to make good the promiſe he had made the day before to his dear Friend, began thus: I told you yeſterday, ſays he, that the Propoſitions contained in the Declaration of my Lords the Biſhops, and in the Theſis main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by Father <hi>Buhi,</hi> are of greater importance than you thought of; and that they contained in them, Truths too evident, and too neceſſary to be let go for the motives of a deluding Peace. To convince you of it, we will make it the ſubject of our preſent Diſcourſe: I believe that the firſt and chief of theſe Queſtions, and which ought to ſerve as a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to all the reſt, is that which concerns the Authority of Councils, which hath ever been moſt venerable among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and which I believe to be of Divine Right, and above the Authority of the Pope: And in this I rely upon the Scripture, and the perpetual and conſtant Tradition of the Church.</p>
               <p>I believe, anſwered <hi>Philéréne,</hi> as you do, That the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Councils is of Divine Right; and no Chriſtian that ever I heard of hath yet diſputed it: But I know not whether you can ſo clearly prove as you hope for, that this Authority of Councils is above that of the Pope, for that many Learned men hold the contrary, and there ſeems to be nothing in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity deciſive upon this matter. The Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> was the firſt that in this caſe pronounced in favour of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils; and what that Council declared about it, was not in an abſolute ſence, but in ſome certain reſpects, and for ſome certain occaſions.</p>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:44415:7"/>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>I acknowledg that there are ſome famous Doctors who are of this opinion, That the Pope is above the Council; but it cannot alſo be denied, but that the number of Learned men who hold the contrary Opinion is much the greater; and you ſhall ſcarce find a Man of Learning in all <hi>France,</hi> but he adheres to their Party.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not for entring upon this particular diſcourſe, but you will oblige me, to ſhew me by good Reaſons, that the Authority of Councils is the ſupream Authority in the Church; and that Believers ought not to acknowledg any other upon Earth in things which relate to Faith and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>To be as good as my word to you then, in what I promiſed you, I ſuppoſe you know the Original of Councils. A Man of your reading in the Divine Hiſtory, cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that God himſelf eſtabliſhed them, when he commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to take to him Seventy Elders for the Government and Conduct of his Ancient people; and you know without doubt that the <hi>Jews</hi> had not only their Council of Twenty three, which they called the <hi>Leſſer Houſe of Judgment,</hi> but alſo their Council of Seventy, wherein preſided their <hi>Anaci,</hi> which Council was compoſed of Sacrificers, Prieſts and Scribes of the Law, and was called the <hi>Greater Houſe of Judgmen.</hi> Our Councils have been formed after this Model, and the Apoſtles began them at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> But to remove all difficulty, our Queſtion ſeems to be clearly decided by our Saviour in the 18th of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> when he referreth them who had any difference, to the Church, if they could not decide it by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, <hi>Dic Eccleſiae,</hi> you ſee our Saviour referreth his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to the Church, without excepting St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf; for which reaſon St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſays very pertinently,<note n="*" place="margin">Ep. 112. Tra. 118. in don. lib. 1. pebapt. con. Donat. cap. 51.</note> That the Church is the laſt and ſupreme Judgment; that St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the Church, when our Saviour ſaid to him, That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he ſhould bind on Earth, ſhould be bound in Heaven; and whatſoever he ſhould looſe on Earth, ſhould be looſed in Heaven; that it is the Church which received the power of the Keys, and that if any one deſpiſeth her when ſhe correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, he ought to be looked upon as a Publican and a Sinner.</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:44415:7"/>
                  <p>It is furthermore the Church which is called the Support and Pillar of Truth.<note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15.</note> 
                     <hi>Columna &amp; firmamentum veritatis.</hi> If you take good heed to this expreſſion of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and to the Reaſons whereon he grounds it, you will agree that the Church is the depoſitary of Truth, and that ſhe hath the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream juriſdiction over her Children for their behaviour; for it is certain in this Text, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> alludes either to the Pillars which were erected in the Heathen Temples, upon which were fixed the Statues and the Deities which were there worſhipped; or to the Two Pillars of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple, one of which was called <hi>Jakin,</hi> and the other <hi>Bohas;</hi> and that he would have us underſtand by it, that it is the Churches Office to declare, to eſtabliſh, and to maintain the Truth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſee very well that the Church being the Spouſe of Jeſus Chriſt, ſhe is made partaker of the advantages and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges which Marriage endoweth her with; and that ſhe being his Body, is as it were clothed with his Majeſty: But St. <hi>Peter,</hi> Was not he made the Head of this Church? Did not Jeſus Chriſt make him his Lieutenant and Vicar, when he ſaid to him, that upon him he would build his Church?<note n="†" place="margin">Matt. 16.18, 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Tu es Petrus &amp; ſuper hanc Petram, &amp;c.</hi> Was it not to St. <hi>Peter</hi> that he gave the Soveraign Authority, when he ſaid to him, <hi>Dabo tibi claves Regni Coelorum &amp; quodcunq, ligaveris ſuper Petram, &amp;c.?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>It is true, that all Catholick Divines do acknowledg St. <hi>Peter</hi> as the Miniſterial head of the Church, and Prince of the Society of the Apoſtles; but this was not a principality of Dominion, which our Saviour expreſly forbiddeth his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles:<note n="‖" place="margin">Matt. 16.18, 19. Luke 22.25. <hi>Item.</hi> Matt. 20.25.</note> 
                     <hi>Reges gentium Dominantur eorum vos autem non ſic.</hi> For which reaſon St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſays, in the 3d Book of his Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations to <hi>Eugenius, Imperium interdicitur, Miniſterium indicitur.</hi> But this is only a Primacy of Order,<note n="⁂" place="margin">Lib. de unit. Eccl.</note> 
                     <hi>Propter bonum unitatis,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Cyprian;</hi> who aſſures us furthermore, that all the Apoſtles, <hi>Erant pari conſortio Honoris &amp; Authoritatis praediti.</hi> Beſides, Was not St. <hi>Peter</hi> a Member of the Church? St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> and St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſays he was, and that with a great deal of reaſon; ſince that all Believers compoſe but one body, to whom Jeſus Chriſt, as the Head, doth communicate the ſpirit of Life. It is then manifeſt, that the Member dependeth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44415:8"/>upon the Body, and not the Body upon the Member. Alſo St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſays upon this Subject, in his Commentary upon St. <hi>Luke,</hi> That the Church is above St. <hi>Peter, Eccleſia eſt ſuper Petrum.</hi> This evidently appears by what St. <hi>Luke</hi> ſays in the 15th of the <hi>Acts,</hi> concerning the firſt Council that was held among Chriſtians, in which Aſſembly of the Apoſtles and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the queſtion which St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>Barnabas</hi> related to them on the behalf of the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> was decided; but they decide it not by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> but by that of the Holy Ghoſt, and of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>Viſum eſt ſpiritui ſancto &amp; nobis, &amp;c.</hi> Alſo in the 21ſt of the ſame Book, St. <hi>James</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, that they had made this Ordinance. St. <hi>Jude</hi> and St. <hi>Silas</hi> are ſent, not on the behalf of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> but of the whole College of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. Add to this, That St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf was ſent with St. <hi>John,</hi> by the Apoſtles, to thoſe of <hi>Samaria,</hi> after they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Word of God, as it is related in the 8th Chapter of the ſame Book, which proves invincibly, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was not the Soveraign Maſter of the Society of the Apoſtles, but that he was in ſome degree their inferior, whatſoever the place were that he held amongſt them; (not unlike the firſt Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the Body of a Senate) it being the right of a Superior to ſend an Envoy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>I apprehend very well what you ſay; But can it be denied, but that Jeſus Chriſt promiſed ſomewhat particularly to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> in the 16th of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> when he ſaid to him in particular, <hi>Ego vero dico tibi, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>I could tell you as a great many Catholick Divines do, That St. <hi>Peter</hi> having anſwered in the name of all the Apoſtles, Jeſus Chriſt gave him nothing in particular; but what he received, he received in the name of all the Apoſtles, and of the whole Church of which he was then the Type, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays, in the 1ſt Book of his Retractations, <hi>Cap.</hi> 21. ſpeaking of St. <hi>Peter, Typum gerebat Eccleſiae cui ſunt traditae claves,</hi> which is founded upon the Text of the 20th of St. <hi>John,</hi> where Jeſus Chriſt gives equally to all his Apoſtles, the power of forgiving and of retaining Sins. I could ſay with St. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> upon this paſſage, and with<note n="(a)" place="margin">De Verb. Dom. Serm. 13. Tract. in <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.4. Serm. de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. 118. in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.97, &amp;c.</note> St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> That this Rock whereon Chriſt promiſeth to build his Church, was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44415:8"/>that firm and ſolid Confeſſion of Faith which St. <hi>Peter</hi> had juſt then made; or elſe Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, who was this Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-ſtone whereon was placed the myſtical building of the Church. <hi>Et ſuper hanc Petram quam cognoviſti,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Auguſtin, dicens tu es Chriſtus Filius Dei viventis, edificabo Eccleſiam meam, id eſt, ſuper me, ipſum Filium Dei edificabo Eccleſiam meam, ſuper me edificabo te, non me ſuper te.</hi>
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Cyril. lib. 4. de Trinit.</note> St. <hi>Cyril,</hi>
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">Hil. lib. 2. &amp; 6. de Trin.</note> St. <hi>Hilary,</hi>
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">Amb. in c. 2. de Epiſto.</note> St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and<note n="(d)" place="margin">Hiero. lib. cont Jov. c. 19.</note> St. <hi>Hierom</hi> are of this opinion; but to deal freely with you, it is none of mine: For I had rather take this Text, as<note n="(e)" place="margin">Tert. lib. 1. de pud. cap. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> and St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and ſay with theſe other Doctors, That Jeſus Chriſt ſpoke in particular to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and promiſed him ſome Prerogatives above his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagues. And to juſtify my Opinion, I obſerve firſt, That St. <hi>Peter</hi> anſwers in particular concerning his Faith. Now Faith is ſo internal a thing, that nothing but the Conſcience of each particular perſon can anſwer for it; and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence we cannot ſay that this Apoſtle anſwered in the name of the whole Society of the Apoſtles. When it concerned ſome outward thing which was obvious to the ſenſes, this Apoſtle might anſwer in the name of all his Brethren, as when he ſays to our Saviour, We have left all to follow thee. <hi>Omnia, &amp;c.</hi> But when the queſtion was concerning a motion of the heart, he could not anſwer for any but himſelf.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, You muſt obſerve that our Saviour promiſeth a particular recompence to the Faith of <hi>Peter;</hi> for which, after that the Apoſtle had ſaid, <hi>Tu es Chriſtus Filius Dei vivi,</hi> He Anſwers him, <hi>Ego vero dico tibi quia tu es Petrus beatus es Simon Barjona,</hi> to make him know, that he would reward particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly the ſtrength of his Faith, and the fervency of his Zeal. For this reaſon he puts him in mind of the new name he had given him, <hi>Tu es Petrus,</hi> ſays he, and furthermore, <hi>&amp; ſuper hanc Petram edificabo Eccleſiam meam.</hi> He makes him under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by this, That he ſhall not bear the name of <hi>Peter</hi> in vain, ſince he intended to build his Church upon this Foundation<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone; and tho the Evangeliſt St. <hi>Matthew</hi> changeth the Term, yet it cannot be inferred from thence that he changeth the Subject; becauſe that <hi>Cephas,</hi> the <hi>Syriack</hi> term, which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour uſed, when he ſaid to <hi>Simon</hi> the Son of <hi>Jona, Thou art Peter,</hi> ſignifies a Rock; ſo that to tranſlate the <hi>Syriack</hi> letter
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44415:9"/>which Jeſus Chriſt made uſe of, we muſt ſay, that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaid to <hi>Simon</hi> the Son of <hi>Jona,</hi> Thou art a Rock, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Rock will I build my Church. And it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was a fundamental ſtone whereon Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt did build his Church, ſince that in the 21ſt of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> the Apoſtles are called,<note n="(g)" place="margin">V. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Fundamenta coeleſtis Jeruſalem.</hi> You will be fully confirmed in this opinion, if you obſerve that the Church is oftentimes compared in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to a Temple, to a Houſe, Believers are the living Stones of it. Jeſus Chriſt is the Corner-Stone, and the Apoſtles the Foundation-ſtones: And of theſe St. <hi>Peter</hi> is to be accounted the firſt, becauſe he laid the firſt foundation of this myſtical build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. To theſe two Obſervations I would add a third, drawn from the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Language, amongſt whom thoſe who beget Children are called the Foundations of Houſes. Who then can doubt in either ſenſe, but that St. <hi>Peter</hi> is one of theſe Foundation-ſtones; nay, the very Foundation-ſtone it ſelf, ſince that by his Preaching, full of Faith and of Zeal, he laid the firſt Foundation of the Chriſtian Church, and begat Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren unto God, as well of the Jewiſh People as of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles?</p>
                  <p>I ſay the ſame thing of what our Saviour added, That he would give him the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven: Theſe Keys are Keys of an Authority; not of Dominion and of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, but of Juriſdiction and of Direction, ſuch as belong to a Steward, and ſuch as God promiſed to lay upon the Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Eliakim</hi> in the 22d of <hi>Iſaiah:</hi> We may alſo ſay, that Jeſus Chriſt alluded to the Cuſtom of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who inveſted their Doctors by the ceremony of delivering to them the Keys; or to the Cuſtom of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who attributed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the power of binding; who called every thing bound which was prohibited; and that looſed which was allowed of. No Man therefore can deny but that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed the principal Doctor of the Chriſtian Church, and that the Keys of Heavenly Knowledg, whereof he juſt then gave an admirable proof, were committed to him. He looſed both the <hi>Jews</hi> and the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> Thoſe from the Obſervation of the Ceremonies of the Law, and the Traditions of their forefathers, which was a grievous burthen; theſe from the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44415:9"/>falſe Opinions and falſe Worſhips wherein they had been bred: And he confirmed both the one and the other in the belief of the Myſteries of Salvation, and in the practice of the Maxims of the Goſpel. In all theſe reſpects, who can doubt but that St. <hi>Peter</hi> received in a particular manner the Keys of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>All that you have ſaid ſeems to me to be very good, and very ſolid; but what had St. <hi>Peter</hi> to his own particular in all this? Are not the other Apoſtles, as well as St. <hi>Peter,</hi> theſe Foundation-ſtones of the Church, in the ſenſe which you have obſerved? Were not the other Apoſtles, as well as St. <hi>Peter,</hi> eſtabliſhed the Infallible Doctors of the Church? Did not they all make uſe of the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven in binding and looſing upon Earth the ſins of Men?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>I agree with you in all you ſay: But though theſe Privileges were common to all the Apoſtles, that doth not at all hinder St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s having them after an Eminent manner; and in this reſpect he had certainly ſome Prerogatives above his Brethren. They were all of them Foundation-Stones whereon Jeſus Chriſt built his Church: But it may be ſaid, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> laid the Foundation of this myſtical building after a moſt ſingular manner, not only becauſe he ſet the firſt hand to it, but alſo becauſe he built this Houſe all the World over, by the means of thoſe, who having been taught immediately from his mouth, and diſperſed at length throughout the World, Preached the Goſpel every where. They all received the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven, but St. <hi>Peter</hi> was the firſt that with his Keys opened the Doors of this Kingdom, and made a larger uſe of it than the others. You ſee alſo that he was the firſt called to the Apoſtleſhip; That he ſhewed alſo a particular zeal and love for his Maſter, who diſtinguiſhed him from the others by his favours, and by the name of <hi>Peter</hi> which he gave him; But all theſe Prerogatives give him only a Primacy of Order, and not of Dominion; an Authority, not of Empire and of Monarchy, but of Precedency and of Direction, ſuch as that of a firſt Preſident in a Senate, or of a famous Philoſopher among thoſe of his Profeſſion; for which reaſon,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Dial. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. cap. 4.</note> St. <hi>Jerom</hi> ſays of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> that he was the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44415:10"/>firſt of the Apoſtles, as <hi>Plato</hi> was the Prince of the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>I am convinced of the truth of what you ſay; But doth it not appear in the 21ſt of St. <hi>John,</hi> that Jeſus Chriſt gives, even an Authority of Dominion to St. <hi>Peter</hi> above his Brethren, whom he diſtinguiſheth by the name of Sheep, as other common believers by the name of Lambs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>You can conclude nothing from that Text in favour of the Monarchical authority of St. <hi>Peter;</hi> for in this place, according to the opinion of<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Cyril. Alex.</hi> lib. 12. in <hi>Joh.</hi> cap. 64.</note> St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and of<note n="(b)" place="margin">Cyril. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſ. <hi>Catech. 2.</hi>
                     </note> St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt did only renew to St. <hi>Peter</hi> the dignity of his Apoſtleſhip, which he enjoyed but as the other Apoſtles did, that he might not think he had loſt it by his three times denying his Maſter; and for this reaſon it is, that he bids him three times to feed his Sheep. It is to no purpoſe to ſeek after a Myſtery in the terms of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſince that the two firſt ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy at the bottom the ſame thing, and the two laſt are given indifferently to Believers in the Scripture. The holy Fathers do alſo hold, that the Apoſtles received the ſame right, and the ſame power as St. <hi>Peter,</hi> when our Saviour ſaid to him, <hi>Paſce oves meas,</hi> according to<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Baſil.</hi> de vit. ſolit. cap. 23. conſti. cap. 42.</note> St. <hi>Baſil,</hi>
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Greg. Naz.</hi> in Teſt. Epiſt.</note> St. <hi>Greg. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen,</hi>
                     <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> in paſſ.</note> St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Aug.</hi> de <hi>Agon.</hi> Chr. cap. 30. lib. queſt. vet. No. Teſt. queſt. 57. &amp; Tract. 47. in <hi>Joh.</hi>
                     </note> St. <hi>Auguſtin.</hi> We might add to this what<note n="(g)" place="margin">Tertull. Carm.</note> 
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſays, That all the Apoſtles had an equal power, and that they were all the ſame as St. <hi>Peter</hi> was, as<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Cypr.</hi> lib. de unitat. Eccleſiae.</note> St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> explains it; and that they had all the ſame dignity, as Pope<note n="(i)" place="margin">Append. com. Theod. Ep. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>Gelaſius</hi> ſays.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>I am very well ſatisfied as to your firſt proof, and I think you have ſhewed ſufficiently by the Holy Scripture, that the ſupream Authority is in the Church, and in the Council which repreſents it; That St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf, tho he were the Prince of the Apoſtles, was ſubject to it; and that he was not looked upon as the ſupreme Judge in things that concerned Religion, but as the firſt Miniſter in the College of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. I deſire you now to paſs on to your ſecond proof, and to ſhew me by the perpetual and conſtant Tradition of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44415:10"/>Church, that the Popes who have ſucceeded St. <hi>Peter,</hi> were never conſidered as the ſupreme arbitrators of things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Religion, but that the Soveraign Authority to which the Popes themſelves ought to be ſubject, was eſteemed ever to be in the Council.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>I will readily perform the promiſe I made to you; but I would have you obſerve by the by, That the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> have not ſucceeded St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the charge of his Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which was a perſonal employment, and particular to thoſe whom Jeſus Chriſt had immediately called, whom he had Bapized by his Holy Spirit, and enriched with extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary gifts, by which means theſe bleſſed people were Infallible, and poſſeſſed a ſoveraign and Independent Authority in the Church, and a Miniſtry which was not reſtrained to a certain place, but which was diſperſed throughout the whole World. I would alſo have you obſerve, That the ſucceſſion of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> was but in the charge of a Biſhop, whereof St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles did communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Rights or Prerogatives to their ſucceſſors; and that this Charge hath this common Right with the Apoſtleſhip, that it confers the power of Preaching the Word, of adminiſtring the Sacraments, and of uſing the power of the Keys; but it gives no infallibility or power of exerciſing the Eccleſiaſtical Miniſtry all the World over. After this Obſervation, which is not amiſs to our purpoſe, I come to what I promiſed you.</p>
                  <p>And I obſerve in the firſt place, that in the moſt Ancient Monuments of Chriſtian Antiquity, I find no traces of this Supreme Power which the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops of the laſt Ages would attribute to themſelves. We have the Epiſtles of St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> which are of an Apoſtolick Character; but there is not ſo much as the leaſt foot-ſtep of this ſupreme Authority attributed to the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> This Holy Prelate ſpeaks of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as of other Churches; He calleth it the Church ſanctified and illuminated by the will of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving it the leaſt authority over any other; and in his 7th Epiſtle to thoſe of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> he directeth it to the Biſhop in the name of the Church, and acknowledgeth nothing above him, which he would never have done, had he believed the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to have been not only above other Biſhops,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44415:11"/>but alſo above a Council. St. <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> in his Apology for the Chriſtians, gives an account to the Emperor <hi>Antoninus,</hi> of the behaviour of Believers in his time, but there is not one word of a ſuperior and ſupreme Maſter that reſided at <hi>Rome,</hi> and made his Soveraign deciſion concerning matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. St. <hi>Polycarp,</hi> the Diſciple of St. <hi>John,</hi> as <hi>Euſebius</hi> relates it, in his Book of Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, came to <hi>Rome</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with <hi>Anicetus,</hi> who was there Biſhop, concerning the day whereon he was to keep <hi>Eaſter;</hi> but yet he followed not this Biſhops Opinion, which without doubt he would have done, if it had been true, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had been at that time held the ſupreme Judge of the Church. St. <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lyons,</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Victor</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> as<note n="†" place="margin">Lib. 5. cap. 2, &amp; 24.</note> 
                     <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith, ſharply reproves him for ſeparating from his Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Church, becauſe they would not keep <hi>Eaſter</hi> upon the ſame day that he did. How could this Biſhop have reproved things of this nature, if he had believed that <hi>Victor</hi> had been in this conjuncture the abſolute judge, to whoſe Deciſions, and to whoſe Tribunal the Church was obliged to ſubmit? There were ſeveral Synods held both in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt;</hi> There was one in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> where <hi>Policrares</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus</hi> preſided, wherein far from acknowledging the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> for the Arbitrator of the whole Church, they condemn his opinion, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> witneſſeth. Was not there a Council alſo held in <hi>France,</hi> our own Country, wherein the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had no ſhare? But St. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> preſided and wrote a very preſſing letter to <hi>Victor,</hi> to oblige him to retain Communion with the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches? Do you think now ſeriouſly, that things would have been carried thus, if they had believed that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had held a Soveraign authority in the Church?</p>
                  <p>Some time afterwards, the Heretick <hi>Novatians,</hi> whoſe Picture <hi>Cornelius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> hath drawn in his Epiſtle to <hi>Fabian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> being deprived of the <hi>Roman</hi> Chair, which he had uſurped, and where he had publiſhed this Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, That they ought not to be admitted to Repentance who had fallen into grievous ſins; <hi>Cornelius</hi> did not undertake of himſelf to condemn this Error, which he would have done without all queſtion, if he had thought himſelf to have been
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44415:11"/>the ſoveraign Arbitrator of the Church, but he aſſembled at <hi>Rome</hi> a Council of Sixty Biſhops. There were alſo held with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any order of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> many Councils in divers places, namely at <hi>Antioch,</hi> which had been an horrible attempt had <hi>Cornelius</hi> been the abſolute Magiſtrate of the Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. <hi>Matthew,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Arles,</hi> having joyned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to <hi>Novatian, Fauſtinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lyons</hi> did not addreſs himſelf to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> but to St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> who wrote to the neighbouring Biſhops of <hi>France,</hi> and to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to exhort them to do their Duty; and in this Letter he ſaith, That he held in his own hand the ballance of the Church Government: Doth not all this then demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively prove, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was not at that time looked upon as the Monarch of the Church? I add to theſe Examples that of the famous Council of <hi>Antioch,</hi> held in the year 265. againſt <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus,</hi> wherein aſſiſted more than 270. Biſhops. This ſworn enemy of our Saviour's Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity being relapſed into the Hereſy which he had formerly abjured in an Aſſembly held in the ſame City, and becauſe he could not be brought back to his Duty, by the Letters and Remonſtrances of the neighbouring Biſhops, it was their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to call a Council; and to this purpoſe <hi>Helenus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> and <hi>Theoctiſtus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> in <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> invited <hi>Dyoniſius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> chief of the Dioceſs of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Firmilian</hi> of <hi>Caeſaria</hi> in <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> chief of the Dioceſs of <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> to the Convocation of a Council, which was at length holden at <hi>Antioch,</hi> without the order of <hi>Faelix</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> and they did proceed againſt <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus,</hi> tho it doth not appear that any body, I won't ſay, preſided, but ſo much as aſſiſted on the behalf of that Biſhop; and at length they ended the Aſſembly by a Synodal Letter which they ſent to <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> whom they thought yet in poſſeſſion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Chair (tho he were dead in the Month of <hi>September</hi> the year before) to <hi>Maternus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and to all their fellow Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons, throughout the whole Earth, and to the whole Catholick Church under Heaven. This had been a very irregular proceeding, if the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had been the ſupreme Magiſtrate of the Church. We may add to this, what the Council of <hi>Alexandria</hi> did in regard
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44415:12"/>of <hi>Origen</hi> under <hi>Demetrius,</hi> for they condemned this Doctor whilſt he was yet living; and alſo under <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> in whoſe Reign they Anathematized his Doctrine and his Memory, and all this without the Order, Intention, or Authority of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> which they had not dared to have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, had they believed that this Biſop had had the ſupreme Authority in the Church. From all this Truth, which I have told you thus at large, may be gathered. That in theſe Primitive Ages of Chriſtianity, the See of <hi>Rome</hi> was really conſidered as the firſt in place, as the Chair of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Center of Prieſtly Unity, as St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> calls it, in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to <hi>Cornelius;</hi> but that it was not looked upon as the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Tribunal of things that concerned Religion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>I gather from this Diſcourſe, that you have now made, that in theſe Primitive Ages, wherein the Holy Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> aſpired to no other Crown than that of Martyrdom, and ſhared nothing amongſt them but the Croſs; before the Spirit of Ambition and of Dominion had entred into the heads of any of theſe Prelates, That the Spirit of Charity and of Humility, which is the ſpirit of the Goſpel, did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly animate them, and that all the Biſhops living in this good underſtanding, and in this union which Jeſus Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends ſo ſtrictly to his Diſciples; they did communicate from one to the other the exigencies and neceſſities of their Churches; that to heal the evils which moleſted them, they choſe out themſelves the remedies which they judged moſt convenient; and the moſt effectual means, and that which they ofteneſt made uſe of, was the Convocation of Synods, to whom the Grace of the Holy Spirit as St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſays, was never wanting for the good and edification of their Flocks. And this which you have now related, brings into my memory many ſuch like methods of our Ancient Biſhops of <hi>France,</hi> which I think I have read in St. <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Tours;</hi> But can you ſhew me in the following Ages this ſame method of acting, and this Tradition of the Church which you have called perpetual and conſtant?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope I ſhall make good my Promiſe; I own that the Heathen Emperors having embraced Chriſtianity, the Church having been enriched by their liberality, and her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44415:12"/>raiſed to a degree of Honour more conſiderable in the World by the effects of theſe Princes Piety, things began to put on another face, and the Biſhops to take place according to the dignity of the Cities wherein they exerciſed their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and to change that deference and honour that was given them before, into a ſort of juriſdiction, as many people have own'd, and among others<note n="*" place="margin">In Anno 39.</note> Cardinal <hi>Baronius,</hi> and as may be gathered out of the 17th Canon of the Council of <hi>Calcedon;</hi> But whatever alteration the Converſion of Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors and of Kings, might have cauſed in the condition of the Prelates, and in the Government of the Church, it cannot be denied but that the Church Government remained ſtill the ſame in ſubſtance, and in what was eſſenrial to it, and that they were always vigorouſly oppoſed, who endeavoured to innovate and to introduce in the Church a Monarchical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; ſo that the Soveraign Authority remained always in the Councils, who in theſe latter Ages have openly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves againſt thoſe who would have robbed them of this privilege.</p>
                  <p>The firſt example that I remember, which juſtifieth the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Authority of the Church, and which proves that the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> were dependants on it, is that of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Arles,</hi> aſſembled, if I am not miſtaken, by the Emperor <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> in the year 314, and compoſed of 200 Biſhops, called together from divers Provinces of the Empire. You know that the Cauſes of this Councils being called, were the differences that happened between <hi>Donatus</hi> of <hi>Caſanigra,</hi> and <hi>Cecilian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> who had been depoſed by an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Biſhops (wherein <hi>Secundus</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Tigifis,</hi> and Primate of <hi>Numidia</hi> preſided) theſe differences having divided <hi>Africa,</hi> ſome Synodal Aſſemblies having eſtabliſhed <hi>Cecilian,</hi> and others <hi>Donatus.</hi> I will not pretend to give an account of this Hiſtory, which you may have read in divers Authors,<note n="†" place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 15. Optat. Mil. cont. adverſ. Parin. lib. 1.</note> and particularly in St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his Epiſtles 68. and 162, where you may ſee how <hi>Conſtantine</hi> commanded the Proconſul <hi>Aelius</hi> to hear all Parties, and to give judgment, and that the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were were there condemned by the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Proconſul. The Schiſmaticks then applied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Emperor, who, to put an end to their differences,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44415:13"/>named firſt of all <hi>Matronus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cologne, Delicius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Autun,</hi> and <hi>Marinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Arles,</hi> and to theſe three he at length joyned <hi>Melciades</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Fifteen other <hi>Italian</hi> Biſhops, of which number was the Biſhop of <hi>Milan;</hi> theſe Nineteen Biſhops gave their judgments in favour of <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilian;</hi> the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> being condemned, Appealed from this judgment, and accuſed their Judges of being too precipitate. What now did the Emperor <hi>Conſtantine?</hi> He did not tell theſe Sectaries, that the judgment that had condemned them had been given by the Soveraign Judge of the Church; but he called a General Council in the City of <hi>Arles,</hi> to examin the matter over again, which had been judged by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the other Eighteen Biſhops, which was done in the preſence of two Prieſts, and two Deacons whom <hi>Sylveſter,</hi> that ſucceeded <hi>Melciades,</hi> had ſent thither, who ſat alſo no higher than in the 5th place. The condemnation of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> was confirmed in this Aſſembly; they alſo decided the queſtion concerning the Baptiſm of Hereticks, and gave it otherwiſe rhan the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had adjudged it, or St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained it; which deciſion held the juſt medium between theſe two Opinions. From hence it appeareth clearly enough, That the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> did not believe himſelf above the Council, ſince that he ſuffered what he had already adjudged to be examined in the Council: It appeareth alſo, that both the Biſhops of thoſe days, and the Emperor <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> believed the Authority of Councils to be Soveraign, and that in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith a Council may decide otherwiſe than the Pope, ſince that the Council of <hi>Arles</hi> did pronounce concerning Baptiſm of Hereticks otherwiſe than the Pope did. You may ſee alſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table proofs of this ſame ſpirit which animated the Biſhops of thoſe times in the famous Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> compoſed of 318 Biſhops, Aſſembled in the 325. year of our Lord, under the ſame <hi>Conſtantine.</hi> The reaſon why this Council was called, was, as you know, the Hereſy of <hi>Arrius,</hi> which ſet all the <hi>Eaſt</hi> in confuſion, and the difference among the Churches concerning the day whereon they ſhould keep <hi>Eaſter.</hi> You know without doubt, that this Hereſiarck having appeared in the year 315, <hi>Alexander</hi> his Biſhop endeavoured to reduce him from his Error. He called together two Councils of all the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44415:13"/>Biſhops of <hi>Egypt,</hi> of <hi>Lybia</hi> and of <hi>Pentapolis,</hi> who depended upon his See, and in theſe Councils <hi>Arrius</hi> was Depoſed and Excommunicated without the mediate or immediate inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to whom <hi>Alexander</hi> thought it ſufficient to gie advice of all that paſſed in the Councils; but the Emperor ſeeing to his great regret that all the care of <hi>Alexander</hi> could not hinder the great progreſs of this Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, he made the famous <hi>Hoſius</hi> to come from <hi>Corduba,</hi> and ſent him to <hi>Alexander</hi> to endeavour to end the difference. All the endeavours of this famous Prelate proving fruitleſs, he joyned his Prayers to thoſe of <hi>Alexander,</hi> and they both of them humbly intreated his Imperial Majeſty to apply a ſpeedy and an effectual remedy to this evil, by the Convocation of an Oecumenical Council. This Great Prince, who had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more at heart than the Glory of God, and the good of his Church, gave a favourable anſwer to the intentions of <hi>Alexander</hi> and of <hi>Hoſius.</hi> He Aſſembled a Council at <hi>Nice,</hi> a City of <hi>Bithynia,</hi> which was opened the 22. of <hi>May,</hi> in the year 325, and ended the <hi>25th.</hi> of <hi>Auguſt</hi> in the ſame year. Never was there in any Aſſembly ſo much Learning and Piety; whatever there was either Learned or Holy in the whole Earth you had in that bleſſed Aſſembly, which hath been and ever will be a Rampart to the true Chriſtian Faith. St. <hi>Sylveſter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> not being able to be there himſelf, aſſiſted by his Envoys, who were <hi>Vitus</hi> and <hi>Vincentius,</hi> Presbyters of his Church. The Admirable <hi>Hoſius</hi> there preſided, and they there ſolemnly condemned <hi>Arrius</hi> and his Doctrine. They there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated the difference about <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and Ordained that it ſhould be Celebrated the Sunday after the Full Moon of <hi>March.</hi> They made in all Twenty five Canons, whereof the Fifth doth prohibit Biſhops to receive to their Communion thoſe who ſhould have been Excommunicated by others; and becauſe thoſe who were Excommunicated might complain that they had been unjuſtly proceeded againſt, it was Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the juſtice of their Excommunication ſhould be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in the Council of Biſhops of each Province. And the Sixth Canon gave bounds and limits to the Dioceſſes of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitans, according to the Ancient Cuſtoms, that thoſe who were ſubject to their inſpection might ſo remain, but alſo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:44415:14"/>that no greater extent ſhould be given them; and that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> ſhould have power in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in <hi>Lybia,</hi> and in <hi>Pentapolis,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> in the Dioceſs which was under him: <hi>Quia</hi> (ſays the Council) <hi>Epiſc. Rom. pariter Mos eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A man muſt wilfully ſhut his eyes not, to ſee in all this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, that in thoſe days it was a vain thing to doubt of the Supreme Authorities being in the Council, and that all Biſhops, he of <hi>Rome</hi> not excepted, were ſubject to it. For firſt of all, you ſee that when <hi>Arrius</hi> would have taught againſt the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Faith, <hi>Alexander</hi> having uſed the way of giving him particular admoniſhment, had no recourſe to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> for the condemnation of this Heretick, but himſelf aſſembled the Council of the Great Dioceſs whereof he was Head; which certainly he would not have done, had he thought that the Supreme Authority belonged abſolutely to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Hoſius</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> having conferred together, and found that the only remedy for this Hereſie was the Convocation of a General Synod, addreſſed themſelves to the Emperor <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> to deſire him to call it: If they had believed that the Soveraign Tribunal of the Church had been the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> why did not they cite <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> thither? Why did they take the way of a Council, which is the longeſt and the moſt difficult? or at leaſt why did they not apply themſelves to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to call it, as hath been done ſince the Popes have raiſed themſelves above theſe Ancient Rules? Thirdly, If the Biſhops of the Council had believed that the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> had had the Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, why did they place <hi>Hoſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Corduba</hi> in the Chair of Preſident, rather than <hi>Vitus</hi> and <hi>Vincentius</hi> the Popes Envoys and Deputies, as hath been practiſed in the late Councils of the <hi>Latin</hi> Church? Fourthly, If theſe Fathers had believed that the laſt Deciſion of Eccleſiaſtical Affairs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the Pope, how would they have dared to ſtart the queſtion upon what day they ſhould keep <hi>Eaſter,</hi> ſince that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had explained himſelf long ſince upon this matter. Fifthly, If the Fathers of this Council had look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Pope as a Superior Judg over the Council, how could they have Ordained that thoſe who had been Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44415:14"/>by one Biſhop, could not be received by another? And how could they have committed to Provincial Synods the Examination of the validity or invalidity of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations? Might not they rather have permitted thoſe who were grieved by the ſentence of Excommunication, to appeal to the See of <hi>Rome</hi> to quaſh or to confirm it as they ſhould think fit? Laſtly, Since they regulate the power of the Biſhop of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> after the example of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> within the limits of the Ancient Uſage, doth not this ſhew that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould not extend his power over other Churches than thoſe which had been under him by the Ancient Cuſtoms; and that he ſhould govern theſe Churches after the ſame manner as the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> did govern thoſe of <hi>Egypt,</hi> of <hi>Lybia,</hi> and of <hi>Pentapolis,</hi> which depended upon him, and that ſo his Authority was reſtrained within certain bounds, and ſubject, as well as that of the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> and other Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litans, to the Authority of the Council?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>You have, methinks, ſufficiently ſhewed by all that paſſed in this Holy and famous Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and form ought for ever to be a Pattern and Model to the Church, that there is no other Soveraign Authority in the Church, than that of Oecumenical Councils; but to confirm me the more in this opinion, do me the favour to ſhew me, that in all other Councils of this nature, they acted after the ſame manner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>As I have already promiſed you, it is juſt that I keep my word to you; but it ſhall be, if you pleaſe, in very few words, and touching only upon what concerns our ſubject; for ſhould I make a relation of all, it would be impoſſible for us to end it in this Diſcourſe. The ſecond Oecumenical Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil held againſt the Heretick <hi>Macedonius,</hi> who diſputed the Divinity of the Holy Ghoſt, was called by the Emperor <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius,</hi> in the City of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Anno 383.</note> though the Pope <hi>Damaſus</hi> deſired that it might be held at <hi>Rome,</hi> as you may ſee in the Synodal Epiſtle of this Council written to <hi>Damaſus,</hi> to <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> and to many others aſſembled at <hi>Rome,</hi> and related by<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Theod.</hi> lib. 5. cap. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>Theodoret,</hi>
                     <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Soc.</hi> lib. 5. cap. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>Socrat.</hi>
                     <note n="(g)" place="margin">Soz. lib. 7. cap. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Sozomen,</hi>
                     <note n="(h)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Nicephor.</hi> lib. 12. cap. 1.</note> and <hi>Nicephorus.</hi> This Council wherein the Pope <hi>Damaſus</hi> neither aſſiſted in perſon, nor by his Deputies, Eſtabliſhed <hi>Nectarius</hi> Patriarch
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:44415:15"/>of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and <hi>Flavian</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Antioch.</hi> It made two Canons which are for our ſubject, namely the Sixth and the Third, the Third importeth, that after the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ought to have the ſame Privileges of Honours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Sixth ſays, that the Biſhop ſhall be judged by the other Biſhops of his Province; and that in caſe of Appeal the matter ſhall be ended by the other Biſhops of the Dioceſs; and laſtly by a General Council. You ſee then, my dear <hi>Philéréne,</hi> that it was the Council which created Patriarchs; which is an act of Supreme Authority, and which clearly ſheweth that the Authority of Patriarchs is ſubalterne and dependant. You ſee that the Councils regulate the place of Patriarchs, giving the ſecond to him of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that this City was the new <hi>Rome,</hi> and placing after him the Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria.</hi> This ſheweth that they followed the ſame order in Eccleſiaſtical Sees, as in Bodie; Politick; and that their addition of Honour and Glory was attributed to the Rank and to the Magnificence of the Cities where they were Eſtabliſhed. You ſee that the Council doth not at laſt ſend Appeals from the Judgments of the Biſhops to the See of <hi>Rome</hi> to be there finally determined, but to an Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menical Council; which ſheweth evidently that this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil did not believe any thing above an Oecumenical Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, and that every thing ought to be ſubject to it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>But do not you know, my dear <hi>Philalethe,</hi> that <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> and after him <hi>Binius,</hi> have ſhewed by many reaſons, that the third Canon of this Council is counterfeit; and that they have affirmed that the Sixth is not to be found in the <hi>Roman</hi> Code, nor in the Abridgements of <hi>Caranza,</hi> and of <hi>Sagittarius?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>I know very well what the Cardinal <hi>Baronius</hi> hath ſaid to make the Third Canon of this Council be ſuſpected; and I know the attempts of the <hi>Latin</hi> Collectors; but you muſt conſult the Originals in <hi>Greek,</hi> which is ſufficient to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat entirely the reaſons of <hi>Baronius.</hi> We ſee in the <hi>Greek</hi> Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginals the Seven Canons that this Council made, among which are the Third and Sixth in the order and in the terms which we have them. Add to this the Evidence of 630 Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, who aſſiſted in the Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> and who in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44415:15"/>the <hi>20th</hi> Canon of this Council, make mention of the <hi>3d</hi> Canon made by the Fathers of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>This gives me ſome ſort of ſatisfaction; but I have one ſcruple more upon this Subject, which is, that it is not likely that the Council of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> that was compoſed of 150 Fathers, would pronounce, upon this matter, quite otherwiſe than the Councill of <hi>Sardica</hi> had done, which was compoſed of Three hundred Biſhops, and held in the year 347, who in their <hi>3d</hi> and <hi>7th</hi> Canons reſerve laſt Appeals to the See of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>I agree with you in what you ſay concerning the Council of <hi>Sardica;</hi> But firſt of all, this Council was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as Oecumenical, tho it were called for that intention. It was added to the <hi>Roman</hi> Code in the year 527. and it was afterward received in the year 591. to the ſecond Canon of the 6th Council, but as a particular Council, and it was pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced after the Councils of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> St. <hi>Gregory</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Greg.</hi> lib. Ep. 24.</note> himſelf doth not reckon it among the Oecumeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Councils. Beſides, you muſt obſerve what was the cauſe of the making of theſe Canons, and in what terms they were expreſt. The Cauſe was the evil dealing which the famous St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> met with at the hand of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Biſhops, who were all <hi>Arrians,</hi> or Demi-<hi>Arrians.</hi> By the 12th Canon of the Council of <hi>Antioch,</hi> which was held in the year 341. it was carried, That a Biſhop being depoſed by the Synod of his Province, ought to addreſs himſelf to a greater Synod, and undergo their judgment, and by this greater was under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Patriarchal Synod, from which there was no Appeal, as may be ſeen, <hi>Nov. Juſt.</hi> 123. <hi>cap.</hi> 22. In the 15th Canon of the ſame Council it is ſaid, That when all the Biſhops of a Province were of one Opinion, there was no Appeal. Now St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> had been condemned by the Synod of his Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, where he ſuſpected almoſt all his Judges, ſince they were his Enemies; as had plainly appeared in their Cabal at the Councils of <hi>Tyre</hi> and of <hi>Antioch,</hi> where the <hi>Euſebians</hi> were the Maſters. What could this Holy Biſhop do leſs than have recourſe to <hi>Julius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who was Orthodox, and to his Council compoſed of Fifty <hi>Weſtern</hi> Biſhops, to ſave himſelf from their oppreſſion? Was not <hi>Julius</hi> and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:44415:16"/>now obliged to maintain, in this conjuncture, the Intereſt of this Man's Injured Innocence, and likewiſe of the Son of God, who was himſelf perſecuted in the perſon of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant? This they did with a great deal of Zeal and Prudence. They declared this Holy perſecuted Man Innocent, and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to the Communion of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who wrote to his paſſionate Judges, exhorting them to appear, not before himſelf, but before a Synod compoſed of lawful Judges, according to the deciſions of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth, that what hath been treated of in one Council, ſhall be examined before another. Theſe unjuſt Judges made a very ill return to the Kindneſs and Charity of <hi>Julius;</hi> they ſent him back a moſt injurious Anſwer; and beſides, being broken up from <hi>Sardica,</hi> where they had been Aſſembled by order of the Emperors, <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> to hold a General Council according to the advice that <hi>Hoſius</hi> had given to <hi>Conſtance,</hi> and retiring to <hi>Philipopolis,</hi> they there held a Factious Cabal, wherein theſe unworthy Prelates Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate <hi>Julius, Hoſius,</hi> and all thoſe who had received St. <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> to their Communion. What now did the true and lawful Council of <hi>Sardica</hi> in this <hi>Caſe?</hi> On one hand they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated theſe wretched men who had bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo raſh as to excommunicate him, and confirmed the Sentence given by <hi>Julius,</hi> and by his Council, in favour of St. <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> and on the other, that the Catholick Biſhops who ſhould be agrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Sentence of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Biſhops, who were the moſt part of them <hi>Arrians</hi> or <hi>Semi-Arrians,</hi> might find a means to free themſelves from their oppreſſion, they declared by the 3d and 4th Canons, That if any perſon ſhould find himſelf agrieved by the Sentence of any Synod of his Province, he might have recourſe from their judgment; in which Caſe the Biſhops of the Province who had judged, ſhould write to <hi>Julius</hi> the Reaſons of their Judgment; That if theſe Reaſons were approved of by <hi>Julius,</hi> the Judgment ſhould hold; but if on the contrary, the Reaſons were not found pertinent, the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould write to the Biſhops of the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Province to examin the matter over a-new, and to judge of it according to the Canons: Wherein you ſee, that the deſign of the Council was only to juſtify the conduct of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44415:16"/>St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> who had had recourſe to <hi>Julius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and likewiſe the behaviour of <hi>Julius</hi> and of his Council, and to provide an effectual remedy for the misfortune of Schiſm, to preſerve Innocence from being oppreſſed in an evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture. But you cannot conclude, from the behaviour of this Council, that the Pope was looked upon as their Superior; on the contrary, it appears plainly, that it was the Council that did acts of Superiority; be it for that they examined a-new the affair of St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> which the Pope and his Council had judged, or for that the Council wrote to the Pope to publiſh his Decrees in <hi>Sicily, Sardinia</hi> and <hi>Italy;</hi> or becauſe they accepted the excuſe which the Pope made them for his abſence; all which things are acts of Superiority: To which we muſt not forget to add, that the Fathers of this Council calling the Pope in the Letter which they wrote to him, their Brother and their fellow Miniſter, makes it very apparent, that they did not acknowledg him for their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior. Beſides, let me advertiſe you, as we proceed, that this Council was not compoſed of 300 Biſhops, as you have ſaid, they were but about 100. and they all <hi>Weſtern</hi> except <hi>Macarius</hi> and <hi>Aſterius,</hi> who were of the <hi>Eaſt.</hi> It is true, that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Conſtantius</hi> had called together this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of Biſhops out of theſe two Empires, and that there came to <hi>Sardis</hi> to the number of 150. as St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> witneſſeth; but all the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Biſhops, who were for the moſt part <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> retired to <hi>Philipopolis.</hi> And altho St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſaith in ſome places, that the Council was compoſed of 300 Biſhops, it is becauſe it was ſubſcribed by a great number of Prelates that did not aſſiſt at it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>Can you ſhew me that the ſame Spirit reigned in the two other great Councils, namely in the Council of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> and in that of <hi>Chalcedon?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>The thing is not difficult; you know the Hiſtory of theſe two Councils, and are not ignorant that the firſt was called by the Emperor <hi>Theodoſius</hi> in the year 431. as may be ſeen in<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Socrat.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 33.</note> 
                     <hi>Socrates,</hi> and in<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Evag.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Evagrius,</hi> and that it was Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled againſt the Hereſy of <hi>Neſtorius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who divided Jeſus Chriſt into two perſons. <hi>Celeſtin</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> being advertiſed of this Hereſy, by <hi>Cyrill</hi> Biſhop of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44415:17"/>
                     <hi>Alexandria,</hi> called together at <hi>Rome</hi> his Synod, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned it, and excommunicated <hi>Neſtorius. Cyrill,</hi> who, for his part, had done all that he could to convince and bring back this wandring Sheep, Aſſembled alſo his Synod, who did no leſs than that of <hi>Rome</hi> had done; but as theſe particular Councils were not a ſufficient remedy, there was called an Oecumenical one in the City of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> whither <hi>Celeſtin</hi> ſent his Legates, namely two Biſhops and one Prieſt, and wherein preſided <hi>Cyrill</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> after whom the firſt of <hi>Celeſtines</hi> Legates was ſeated. Here were made Eight Canons, of which the eighth makes chiefly for our purpoſe: For to reſtrain the attempts of the Patriarch of <hi>Antioch</hi> upon the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Churches of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> it ordaineth, that not only in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> but in all other Dioceſſes and Provinces of the World, no Biſhop ſhould uſurp any Province, which from the beginning had not been of his dependance; and that every Province ſhould preſerve inviolably the Rights which ſhe hath had from the beginning, and according to the Ancient Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom. Who can ſay but that this Council doth all the acts of a Supreme Authority? And that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> doth none at all? If he had had any, after that he and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil had condemned <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> it had not been neceſſary to call a General Council for it; the firſt of his Legates would, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion, have preſided in this Council, and this Holy Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly would not have undertaken to make General Decrees, which limit the Power of all Biſhops, without excepting even him of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You have alſo read, without doubt, what the ſame <hi>Socrates</hi> ſays of the Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> called by the Emperor <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianus</hi> in the year 451. to ſtifle the Hereſy of <hi>Eutiches,</hi> who confounded the two Natures in Jeſus Chriſt; you may thence have learned, that a General Council having been called by <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the ſecond, in the City of <hi>Epheſus, Eutiches,</hi> by the intrigues and artifices of <hi>Dioſcorus,</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> ſet himſelf in this Factious Cabal, againſt <hi>Flavian,</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who was there depoſed, becauſe he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and condemned this Heretick; for which Reaſon this unhappy Aſſembly was called <hi>Latrocinium,</hi> or the <hi>Robbery,</hi> that at length the Orthodox Biſhops, as namely <hi>Leo</hi> the great, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44415:17"/>of <hi>Rome,</hi> as may be ſeen in the 23, 25, and 26 of his Letters, intreated the Emperor to call an Oecumenical Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, which becauſe <hi>Theodoſius</hi> either could not or would not do, <hi>Martianus,</hi> who ſucceeded him, did it, having Aſſembled this Council, not at <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>Leo</hi> would have had it, but firſt at <hi>Nice,</hi> and then at <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> as is to be ſeen in the 43, 44, 49, 50, and 51 of this Popes Epiſtles. This Council compoſed of 630 Biſhops, reſtored the memory of <hi>Flavian,</hi> by condemning and depoſing <hi>Dioſcore</hi> and <hi>Eutiches.</hi> They made many Canons; in their 17th it is ordained, that the order of Pariſhes in the Church ſhould be according to the Politick and Civil form. In the <hi>29th.</hi> they Decree, that a Clergy-man, having a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with his Biſhop, ſhall be judged by the Synod of his Province; and if a Biſhop hath a difference with the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan of the Province, let him addreſs himſelf to the Exarch of the Dioceſs, or to the Biſhop of the Royal City of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople.</hi> And in the <hi>28th</hi> they do ordain, That according to the deciſion of 150 Fathers of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> Privileges equal to thoſe of old <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhould be given to the moſt Holy See of New <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe ſhe was honoured with the ſeat of the Empire and of the Senate; and that in things Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſhe ought not to be held in leſſer dignity, tho ſhe took but the ſecond place. A Man muſt wilfully ſhut his eyes, not to ſee that this Council did not conſider the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> as having in his hands the Supreme Authority, ſince that they do not ſend the differences that might happen between Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and their Metropolitans to him for their laſt determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that they make the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> equal to him in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, reſerving to him ſimply the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy of Order, becauſe his See was the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> where the Emperors and the Senate formerly did reſide: To which we ought to add, what we read in the Letter of the Fathers of this Council to <hi>Leo</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> where they ſay freely, That they had appointed and confirmed what had been alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ordain'd by the Council of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> tho <hi>Leo</hi>'s Legates oppoſed it, wherein they tell him, that he ought to acquieſce, not only for the conſervation of Order, but alſo out of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the Emperors, who had given them ſo abſolute an Authority, that their Judgments paſſed for a Law, reflecting
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44415:18"/>without doubt, upon the Ordinance of <hi>Valentinian</hi> the third, made in favour of the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> Laſtly, We ought to obſerve, That the Fathers who compoſed this Council, found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not the Privilege of Epiſcopal Sees, but upon the Civil and Politick Prerogatives of the Cities where they were; which ſheweth, That the Eminence of that of <hi>Rome,</hi> was not found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Primacy of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who had been the firſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of it, ſo much as upon the dignity of the City. I could add to the Authority of theſe four great Councils, that of the ſecond Council of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which is the Fifth Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menical one, called by the Emperor <hi>Juſtin,</hi> in the year 553. to condemn the writings of <hi>Theodorus Mopſueſtia,</hi> thoſe of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret,</hi> and the Epiſtles of <hi>Ibas</hi> to <hi>Maris;</hi> for this Council ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited <hi>Vigilius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to judge the Queſtion which they were handling, not ſeparately from them, but conjointly with them: And the Emperor <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> in his Letters to <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichius</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and to <hi>Apollinarius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, That the care of Emperors hath always been to extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate Hereſies, and to preſerve the purity of the Faith by the means of Councils; which ſheweth clear enough, what ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Judge was acknowledged in the Church: I might joyn to the Authority of this <hi>5th</hi> Oecumenical Council, that of the <hi>6th</hi> and <hi>7th,</hi> which make but one, this laſt having only added ſome Canons to the deciſions of the ſixth, which was held under <hi>Conſtantine Pogonatus,</hi> in the Palace called <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ullum;</hi> ſince that, in the <hi>36th</hi> Canon of this laſt Council, were confirmed the Canons of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> which made the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> and of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> equal in Eccleſiaſtical Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; and condemned <hi>Honorius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> with many others, as tainted with the Hereſy of the <hi>Monotholites;</hi> but our Diſcourſe hath already been ſo long, that I ought not to tire out your patience any further.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not at all wearied with your Diſcourſe; but it is not fit to exact too much upon your kindneſs, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the other reflections which you can make upon this Subject, to another converſation.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:44415:18"/>
               <head>The Third Dialogue.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PHilér.</speaker>
                  <p>You were ſo kind, my dear <hi>Philalethe,</hi> in our laſt walk, to make me hope for ſome more of your reflections upon the ſubject whereon we were diſcourſing. I'le be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to you if you will impart them to me now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>I will purſue this matter ſince you deſire it; but you will not take it amiſs if I abridg it as much as I can. After the Authority and Judgment of Oecumenical Councils, I ſee nothing of greater force than what paſſed in the <hi>African</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, and namely in the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Council held in the Month of <hi>Auguſt</hi> of the year 402, wherein St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> aſſiſted, as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in his <hi>117th.</hi> Epiſtle: In this Council they confirmed what had been decreed againſt the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> by a former Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Carthage;</hi> and in the Sixth Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> which was the Univeſal of <hi>Africa,</hi> begun in the year 418, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to the year 423. In the firſt of theſe Councils they made a Canon, which is the 22, or the 31 according to <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zamon,</hi> by which it was Ordained that Prieſts, Deacons, and other Clergymen ſhould appeal from the Judgment of their Biſhops to the other Neighbouring Biſhops, and from them to the Council of <hi>Africa,</hi> or to the Primate, and to no other up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pain of Excommunication, as it hath been Ordained here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore concerning Biſhops. You may ſee it thus expreſſed in the <hi>Greek</hi> Copies in <hi>Zonaras,</hi> and in ſome <hi>Latin</hi> Copies, and in the Council of <hi>Rheims</hi> held under <hi>Hugh Capet</hi> where this <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levitan</hi> Council is alledged. It is true that<note n="*" place="margin">1 Canſ. 2. qu. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Gratian</hi> excepts Appeals to the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> but that was added of his own head, ſince it was Appeals themſelves which theſe Fathers did deſign wholly to prohibit. In the ſecond of theſe Councils, which is the Sixth of <hi>Carthage,</hi> compoſed of 207 Biſhops, of whoſe number was St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and wherein preſided <hi>Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> they again had reaſon to renew this Decree againſt Appeals beyond Sea; and ſee here the occaſion: <hi>Apiarius</hi> Presbyter of <hi>Sicca</hi> in <hi>Numidia,</hi> was Depoſed and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44415:19"/>for his Crimes by ſome Biſhops; he Appealed from their Sentences before the Pope <hi>Zoſimus,</hi> who by the judgment that he gave declared him innocent, and delivered him from the Penalties to which he had been condemned. This <hi>Apiarius</hi> having acknowledged his fault before the Council, and there asked pardon for it, was reſtored to the Exerciſe of his Charge, but not in the Church of <hi>Sicca,</hi> by reaſon of the Scandal he had there given. This wretched fellow falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into his Diſorders, was Depoſed by <hi>Sylvanus</hi> his Biſhop. He Appealed again from this Judgment to <hi>Celeſtin,</hi> who then held the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Pope ſent the Biſhop <hi>Fauſtinus</hi> to the Council, with two Presbyters, to maintain theſe the Rights of his See. <hi>Fauſtinus</hi> acquitted himſelf very well in his Commiſſion: He repreſented that by virtue of the Canons of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> it was allowable to Appeal to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> and demanded that the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Canon ſhould be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled, which prohibited Appeals beyond the Seas. The Biſhops being ſurprized upon what <hi>Fauſtinus</hi> had ſaid, becauſe he ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Canon wholly unknown to them, conſulted the Copy of the Acts of the Council of <hi>Nice.</hi> The procedure in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair of <hi>Apiarius</hi> having been lawfully done, they confirmed the condemnation from which he had Appealed, and wrote a Synodical Letter to <hi>Celeſtin,</hi> which was Superſcribed in theſe Terms, <hi>To our moſt Dear and Honourable Brother</hi> Celeſtin. And in this Letter they deſire him not to receive to his Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion thoſe whom they ſhould Excommunicate, according to the Decrees of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> which have ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ected as well inferior Clergymen as Biſhops to their Metropolitans, willing that Affairs ſhould be determined where they began; aſſuring themſelves that the Grace of the Holy Spirit would never be wanting to every Province; and after having ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him the inconveniencies that would follow theſe ſorts of Appeals, they give him to underſtand that they had not found in the Acts of the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> which had been ſent them from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and from <hi>Antioch,</hi> this Canon which <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinus</hi> had alledged. Not ſatisfied with this Letter which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained their Opinions, they make a Canon which renewed that of the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Council, ſignifying that Prieſts, Deacons, and other inferior Clergymen ſhould not Appeal beyond the Seas,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44415:19"/>but to the Primate of their Provinces, as hath been often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved concerning Biſhops. Who is there now but ſeeth that the Fathers of this Council did not believe that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had the Supreme Authority in the Church, ſince that not only his Legate <hi>Fauſtinus</hi> did not preſide in it, but was ſeated after <hi>Valentinus</hi> Biſhop of the firſt See of <hi>Numidia;</hi> that they examin over again the Affair of <hi>Apiarius,</hi> as though it had not been judged by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> that they give him only the name of Brother, and will not at all permit that any Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Africa</hi> ſhould appeal to <hi>Rome?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>This indeed appears very ſtrong; but do not you know that it is generally agreed, that in the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Canon, there is nothing ſaid of the Biſhops? and that the clauſe that concerns them hath been ſince added? that beſides the Canon produced by <hi>Fauſtinus</hi> to his Colleagues, was in ſome reſpects a Canon of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> ſince that it was of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Sardica,</hi> which is but an Addition, a Supplement, and as it were the Seal of the Council of <hi>Nice?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe Interpretations appear to me but weak; for the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Canon in the <hi>Greek,</hi> and in ſome <hi>Latin</hi> Copies, doth comprehend the Clauſe concerning Biſhops. Beſides, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of this Council of <hi>Africa,</hi> in the Epiſtle which they wrote to <hi>Celeſtin,</hi> make it known ſufficiently that they did not underſtand that Biſhops could appeal beyond the Seas, no more than other inferior Clerks, ſeeing that at the ſame time which they wrote this Epiſtle, they had before them not only the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal of <hi>Apiarius,</hi> but alſo that which <hi>Anthony</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Foſſat</hi> had brought againſt the Sentence of his Provincial Synod be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> who reſtored him; for which reaſon<note n="†" place="margin">Epiſt. 162.</note> St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> wrote a Letter to <hi>Celeſtin,</hi> this Popes Succeſſor, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe pretended Additions to the Council of <hi>Nice;</hi> for that of <hi>Sardica</hi> was called by different Emperors, in a far di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant place, and after a conſiderable Interval of time; for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and Reaſons alſo different, as every body knoweth that hath any knowledg of Hiſtory. If this Council had been a Supplement of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> as they pretend, why is it not placed in the order of Oecumenical Councils? Whence comes it that the Fathers of the Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> amongſt whom were St. <hi>Auguſtin, Aurelius,</hi> and <hi>Alipandus,</hi> the moſt famous Biſhops of their time, were ignorant of this Canon?
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44415:20"/>And why did not <hi>Fauſtinus</hi> ſay plainly, that this Canon was tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Council of <hi>Sardica,</hi> rather than that it was of equal authority to the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> to which it was but the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement and the Seal?</p>
                  <p>I will not enlarge to you upon what paſſed in the year 397, in the Council of <hi>Turin,</hi> where they judged the difference that was between <hi>Proclus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> and Metropolitan of the firſt Province of <hi>Narbonne,</hi> and the Biſhops of the ſecond Province, who would not depend upon him; and the conteſt that there was between the Biſhops of <hi>Arles</hi> and of <hi>Vienne,</hi> concerning the honour of Primacy, and the right of Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which the Fathers of this Council would not have da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to undertake, had they believed that the Soveraign Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity had belonged to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> You may learn the ſame thing from what paſſed in the Council of <hi>Toledo,</hi> againſt the <hi>Priſcilianiſts,</hi> and of the conjunction which theſe Fathers make of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Milan,</hi> and of <hi>Siricus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> Nor will I entertain you with the Council of <hi>Francfort,</hi> called by the Emperor <hi>Charlemagne</hi> in the year 794, wherein aſſiſted the Biſhops of <hi>France,</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> and of <hi>Italy,</hi> wither the Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> ſent his Legates, and wherein the Canon of the ſecond Council of <hi>Nice</hi> concerning the Religious Worſhip of Images was annulled, though this Council had been appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of by <hi>Adrian.</hi> I will not ſpeak to you neither of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils which were held in <hi>France</hi> our own Country, which vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly oppoſed this immoderate Worſhip which the ſecond Council of <hi>Nice</hi> would have eſtabliſhed, and which the Popes maintained to their utmoſt. In good faith now, if the Fathers of the Council of <hi>Francfort,</hi> or if the Prelates of <hi>France</hi> had believed the See of <hi>Rome</hi> to be Soveraign, would they have ſpoken, would they have acted as they did?</p>
                  <p>I come now to the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> held in the year 1414. whoſe Authority and Deciſion my Lords the Biſhops make uſe of to ſupport their opinion. He that will penetrate well into the ſpirit of this Council, muſt take the thing in its original, and obſerve that a lamentable Schiſm had raged near 30 years, and produced a great many evil effects during the Pontificate of <hi>Peter de Luna,</hi> called <hi>Benedict</hi> the <hi>13th.</hi> and under that of <hi>Angelus Corrarius,</hi> called <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>12th,</hi> Anti-popes; the Cardinals of either party being Aſſembled, agreed for the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44415:20"/>putting an end to theſe Schiſms, to call a Council at <hi>Piſa:</hi> This Council being Aſſembled in the year 1409. declares, That this Affair belonged to them, as they repreſented the Univerſal Church, and they condemned <hi>Peter de Luna,</hi> and <hi>Angelus Corra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> as notorious Schiſmaticks, defenders and favourers of Schiſm, Hereticks, and as having deviated from the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> After the depoſing of theſe two Anti-popes by the Council, the Cardinals who there aſſiſted, choſe <hi>Peter de Candia</hi> Pope, who was called <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>5th,</hi> and who lived but about Ten months: After his death the ſame Cardinals elected the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Balthaſar</hi> of St. <hi>Euſtace,</hi> who called himſelf <hi>John</hi> the 23. or 24. Thus there were three Anti-popes who condemned one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. To find out a remedy for this diſorder, the Emperor <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> adviſed Pope <hi>John,</hi> to order that the Council of <hi>Piſa</hi> ſhould be continued in the City of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> whereupon this Pope called thither all thoſe that had a deliberative voice, the Emperor, and all Chriſtian Princes. Pope <hi>John</hi> opened the Aſſembly in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors preſence; and in the ſecond Seſſion he would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the Papacy, provided his competitors would do the ſame; but they refuſing, they were all three judged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the Council; Pope <hi>John</hi> for many crimes whereof he was accuſed and convicted, and the others for the ſame reaſons that they had been condemned at <hi>Piſa;</hi> and they choſe <hi>Odo Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomna</hi> Pope, who called himſelf <hi>Martin</hi> the <hi>3d</hi> or the <hi>5th;</hi> And to the end that no man might doubt of the power which the Council had of Judging Soveraignly in all Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, they, in their <hi>4th</hi> Seſſion, made this following Canon:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The General Council lawfully Aſſembled in the name of the Holy Ghoſt, and repreſenting the Catholick Church militant, holdeth immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately its power from Jeſus Chriſt; to which Council, all manner of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of what eſtate or quality ſoever, nay the Pope himſelf, is bound to obey in things which concern the Faith, the extirpation of Schiſms, and the General Reformation of the Head and Members.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And for as much as in the <hi>39th</hi> Seſſion this Council did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, that for time to come there ſhould be held a General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil at the end of every Ten years, and that the next Council ſhould be called in Five years, and the following one in Seven, the Council accordingly was called together at <hi>Pavia,</hi> where it began, and was afterward continued at <hi>Siena,</hi> and finally in 1431. it was transferred to <hi>Baſil,</hi> where it was decided according to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:44415:21"/>the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> that it was a moſt Catholick truth, that Councils were above Popes, and that Popes could not by their own wills either diſſolve, or prorogue Councils from place to place.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Have you no other proof which juſtifieth this Opinion? And have not there been Popes who have acknowledged the ſuperiority of Councils?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>There are many other proofs which might be made uſe of, which are even of the ſame kind as thoſe whereof we have already ſpoken; for we might remember ſeveral examples of the Ancient Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> who have ſuffered their judgments to be examined in General Councils; and have ſubmitted themſelves to their Decrees; nay there are ſome who have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that the Decrees which they had made might be examined in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil; and amongſt others, <hi>Leo</hi> the Great, who demanded of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> that what he had decreed, as well as what had been decreed in the pretended Council of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> ſhould be examin'd in a Gen. Council. There have been alſo many other Popes that have acknowledged the Tribunal of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Councils, and amongſt others the Pope <hi>Damaſus,</hi> who diſputing with <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſicinus</hi> concerning the Pontificate, ſubmits himſelf to the judgment of a Synod, which decided this Affair; and when this Pope was accuſed of Adultery by two Deacons, <hi>Concordius</hi> and <hi>Caſtorius,</hi> he juſtified himſelf before a Council of 44 Bps. Aſſembled at <hi>Rome,</hi> in the year 378. I could add the evidence of ſeveral Popes upon this ſubject, and amongſt others, that of <hi>Zozimus,</hi> who in his <hi>1ſt</hi> Ep. ſays, That the Authority of his See cannot add nor change any thing againſt the Ordinances of the Holy Fathers, which is a mark of ſubjection, and of dependence. And alſo that of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, who, in ſome place proteſted that he reverenced the Authority of the four Great Councils, like that of the four Goſpels.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philér.</speaker>
                  <p>Were I not afraid of treſpaſſing upon your patience, I would deſire you to give me ſome particular account of our <hi>Gadican</hi> Church, and to let me know, whether ſhe always believed the Superiority of the Councils above the Popes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>I will do it, my dear <hi>Philéréne;</hi> but it ſhall be but very ſhort, that I may not tire you. It cannot be doubted but that in the firſt Centuries, our Churches of <hi>France</hi> acknowledged the Authority of Councils as ſuperior to all others, ſince that in the queſtion concerning the day of Celebrating <hi>Eaſter,</hi> our Prelates with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the knowledg and participation of the Pope, called a Synod, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in St. <hi>Irenae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> preſided, who by order of the Synod wrote a Letter, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly preſſing, to Pope <hi>Victor</hi> about this Affair, as may be ſeen in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius;</hi> which this Biſhop would never dare to have done if the Pope had been conſidered in the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church as the Supreme Magiſtrate of the Church; and the Decretal Epiſtles attributed to the firſt Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> cannot be objected to the contrary, becauſe that theſe Epiſtles have ſuch viſible characters of being counterfeited, that it is beyond all doubt. And in the Council of <hi>Arles,</hi> above mentioned, our Biſhops of <hi>France</hi> ſhewed ſufficiently that the Pope was ſubject to the Authority of Councils, ſince that they examined an Appeal brought before them from the Popes Sentence. Since that time divers Synods have been held in <hi>France</hi> by the order and permiſſion of our Kings, to treat of things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Faith or Diſcipline of the Church, wherein they judged of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aith by the Oracles; of the Scripture, and by Tradition; and of Diſcipline
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:44415:21"/>by the Canons of the Church, that is to ſay of Councils. Such was, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that which, was held in the reign of our K <hi>Clovis</hi> at <hi>Orleance,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Alſo the ſecond Council of <hi>Maſcon</hi> Ordained, that Provincial Councils ſhould be called by the Metropolitans, and that of the whole Kingdom by the Biſhop of <hi>Lions,</hi> with the Kings permiſſion. It is true, that the <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican</hi> Church received a great abridgment of its Liberties in the year 445, by the Ordinance of <hi>Valentinian</hi> the <hi>3d,</hi> who made the judgments of all the <hi>French</hi> Prelates ſubject to the Pope But this Ordinance of <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinian</hi> received divers oppoſitions in <hi>France,</hi> as it were eaſie to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie by many famous examples. In the 8. Century the Churches of <hi>France</hi> received another blow, by introducing the Code of the <hi>Roman</hi> Canons, which <hi>Charlemaign</hi> obliged himſelf to receive in <hi>France,</hi> as well as the <hi>Roman</hi> Office, in acknowledgment of the good turns which Po. <hi>Adrian</hi> had done him, who in an Aſſembly of 15 Biſhops, and many Abbots de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared <hi>Charlemaign Patrician,</hi> or a Nobleman of <hi>Rome,</hi> and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that it was in his power to Elect Popes, to regulate the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick See, to inſtitute through all the Provinces Archbiſhops and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; in a word he inveſted him with all the Rights which the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperors enjoyed: Nevertheleſs this great Prince found in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceution of his promiſe great oppoſition from the Clergy whom he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to receive the Code of theſe aforeſaid Canons by conſtraint, <hi>Minis &amp; Suppliciis,</hi> ſays the Original; nor were theſe Canons received but by the Authority of our Kings, having been publiſhed but under the name of <hi>Charlemaign,</hi> and as Ordinances made by him His Succeſſors have trod in the ſame footſteps, always ordering that the Laws which they made by the advice of the Prelates of their Kingdoms, and which are to be read in their <hi>Capitulars</hi> ſhould be publiſhed under their Majeſties Names, and that the Popes themſelves ſhould be ſubject to them <hi>C. de Capi, &amp; deſtin.</hi> 10. and <hi>C. nos de Compet</hi> 2. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 7. But whatever increaſe the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Pope had gained in <hi>France</hi> by this Ordinance of <hi>Valentinian,</hi> and by this Introduction of <hi>Charlemaign,</hi> this did not hinder our Biſhops from ſhewing upon all occaſions a great deal of vigor in maintaining their Privileges, and the Authority of the Church. It is manifeſt by divers Examples which Hiſtory affordeth, and chiefly by that of <hi>Hincmare</hi> B. of <hi>Laon;</hi> this Prelate was cenſured and condemned for his ill actions by a Synod held at <hi>Vervins;</hi> he would have appealed to <hi>Rome,</hi> but far from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any regard to his appeal he was forthwith condemned for his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, in a Synod of ten Provinces held at <hi>Attini.</hi> We may add to this example of <hi>Hincmare,</hi> that of <hi>Arnulph</hi> A B. of <hi>Rheims,</hi> who was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and depoſed for ſeveral crimes in an Aſſembly of many Biſhops held at <hi>Rheims,</hi> who declared that they acted by the Authority which had been given to the Apoſtles, and which had been left to them. This ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſheweth that an Apoſtolick ſpirit reigned in the ſouls of our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, and that in ſpight of the enterprizes and attempts of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> they maintained this general opinion of their worthy Predeceſſors, That they held their charges and the authority which belongeth to them from God, and not from the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> They ſhewed the ſame zeal in the A B. of <hi>Sens</hi> his Affair at the Synod of <hi>Pontignon,</hi> and in that of <hi>Saire,</hi> concerning a Church in the Dioceſs of <hi>Tours,</hi> held by a Cardinal
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:44415:22"/>ſent by <hi>John</hi> the 20. Which they call a Sacriledg and a contradiction to the Holy Canons, which ordain that a Biſhop can do nothing in anothers Dioceſs without his conſent. And in that of <hi>Geofry</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chartres,</hi> in whoſe place one <hi>Ivo</hi> had been ſurrogated by Pope <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban 2d,</hi> whom <hi>Richarius</hi> A B. of <hi>Sens,</hi> Mertropolitan of <hi>Chartres,</hi> together with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Paris, Troys,</hi> and <hi>Meaux</hi> oppoſed. They alſo ſhewed this ſame ſpirit in the advice they gave to <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Auguſt,</hi> to appeal to the next Council from the Sentence of <hi>Innocent</hi> 3, as from an abuſe, in the Prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick Sanction which St. <hi>Lewis</hi> made by their advice; and in the Council which they gave together with others aſſembled at <hi>Paris</hi> in the year 1209 to <hi>Philip</hi> the Fair againſt the enterprizes of <hi>Boniface</hi> 8, not to mention the famous Book call'd <hi>Somnium Viridarii,</hi> writ and publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the order of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, called the <hi>Wiſe;</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Laws and Rules wich <hi>Charles</hi> the 6. his Son made againſt the Uſurpations of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> which ſheweth ſufficiently that the Authority of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> was not looked upon as the ſuperior Authority in <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But after that the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> had formally explained it ſelf upon this matter, men ſpoke bolder in <hi>France</hi> than they had done in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times. <hi>Charles 7th.</hi> forbad the <hi>French</hi> Prelates to go to the Council called at <hi>Ferrara</hi> in the year 1427. And he himſelf called in the City of <hi>Bourges</hi> a great and famous Aſſembly of the Princes of his Blood, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of his Crown, Prelates and Eccleſiaſtical perſons, members of his great Council, Doctors in Law, as well Divine as Humane, and Profeſſors of the Univerſities, together with the Legates of <hi>Eugenius 4th.</hi> After that the Doctors of the Univerſities had repreſented in the name of the whole <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, her former ſtate, her Rights, and the attempts which had been made upon her Liberties; they beſought his Majeſty to remedy this diſorder, that he would be pleaſed to Authorize ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and Canons of the General Councils of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and of <hi>Baſil;</hi> ſuch as that is which declares, that General Councils lawfully aſſembled, and repreſenting the Church militant, have their power immediately from Jeſ. Chriſt, and are above the Pope, which Councils they themſelves had judged ought to be obſerved. Wherupon the King approved &amp; confirmed the aforeſaid decrees &amp; ordered all people to obſerve and keep them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violaby. This is that which was called the pragmatick Sanction. 32 years afterwards <hi>Lewis</hi> 11. being won by the flatteries of <hi>Pius 2d,</hi> and through evil ſuggeſtions, as may be ſeen in the Book of the three Eſtates of the year 1483, revoked the Pragmatick Sanction without any conſultation of the States before hand, or of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church. The Kings At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torny General, and the Rector of the Univerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> formally op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the Regiſtring the Kings Letters concerning theſe his Decrees. The Court of Parliament it ſelf repreſented in writing the great evils that would happen upon the aboliſhing of ſo juſt a Sanction, to ſo good effect, that <hi>Lewis 11th.</hi> far from aboliſhing it, gave orders for its confirmation, as amongſt others that of the 16 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1478, whereby it is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to go the <hi>Rome</hi> to ſeek after any Benefice, or to pay in any money, upon pain of Confiſcation of Body and Goods; and to prevent <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi>'s from <hi>Rome,</hi> he cauſed his Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> at the requeſt of his Attorny-General to paſs an Act, that in caſe the Pope ſhould undertake
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44415:22"/>any thing to the prejudice of his Ordinances, he ſhould appeal to the next Council.</p>
                  <p>The Eſtates of the Kingdom, whereof the Clergy is the firſt Order, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Aſſembled at <hi>Tours,</hi> preſent a Petition to King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>8th,</hi> in the firſt Article of which, they deſire His Majeſty to keep, and maintain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably the Pragmatick Sanction of <hi>Bourges,</hi> founded upon the Decrees of the Councils of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and of <hi>Baſil.</hi> And in the National Council, which <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>12th</hi> Aſſembled in the ſame City of <hi>Tours,</hi> in the year 1510, the obſervation of the Pragmatick Sanction was fully reſolved upon. Obſerve how our venerable Prelates have ever maintained the Intereſt and the Privileges of the Church, againſt the attempts of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and how they make appear to the whole World, that they do Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly keep in their hearts the Sentiments which they had received from their Anceſtors, &amp; that they believed that the ſupreme Authority re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided in General Councils; and that how eminent ſoever that of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> might be, it was ſtill dependant upon theirs. This is the Doctrine which hath been taught and maintained by the Univerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> as may be ſeen in the Writings of her moſt famous Doctors, ſuch as are the Chancellor<note n="(c)" place="margin">Tract. de poteſt. Eccleſ.</note> 
                     <hi>Gerſon, James Almain,</hi> &amp;c. to which to may add a great many more, as<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Cuſ. de concord. can. lib. 2. cap. 2.</note> the Cardinal of <hi>Cambray, Nicho, Cuſan,</hi>
                     <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pan.</hi> in cap. ſignif. extrav. de elect.</note> the Abbot <hi>Panormitan,</hi>
                     <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Abulenſis</hi> in cap. 18. <hi>Matt.</hi> quaeſt. 108.</note> 
                     <hi>Abulenſis,</hi>
                     <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Fran.</hi> vict. T. de potes. Eccleſ.</note> 
                     <hi>Franciſcus de Victoria,</hi>
                     <note n="(h)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Alph.</hi> a <hi>Caſt.</hi> lib. 7. de juſt. pun. haer.</note> 
                     <hi>Alphonſus a Caſtro,</hi> and all the Divnes of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> which is ſpoken of in the <hi>7th</hi> Book of the Hiſtory of this Council, who maintained with our Biſhops of <hi>France,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Spain,</hi> that the juriſdiction of Biſhops, and their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence was of Divine Right.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philer.</speaker>
                  <p>All that you have ſaid, perſwades me ſufficiently, that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Councils is above that of the Popes; but there are ſome ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples that I deſire to be reſolved in, before that I can cordially embrace your Opinion; Theſe ſcruples ariſe from two things wherein you will agree with me. The one is, That the Popes have been ever deſired to confirm Councils, which without doubt had never been, if their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity had not depended on that of the Popes. And the other is, That the Title of Head of the Council is given to the Pope, and namely in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Councils of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and of <hi>Chalcedon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phila.</speaker>
                  <p>What you ſay cannot be diſproved, but I think that the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences that you draw from theſe Principles are not right; for you muſt in the firſt place acknowledg that the conſent to, an confirmation of General Councils, was deſired of all great Sees, which did not regard the Decrees of Councils as Obligatory, till after they had themſelves conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them. Thus the Decree of the Council of <hi>Epheſus</hi> againſt <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> was of no force in the Eaſt, till that <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and all the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politans depending upon his Dioceſs had agreed to it; And the judgment of the <hi>5th</hi> General Council againſt the <hi>Tria Capitula,</hi> was without force till the Dioceſſes of <hi>Africa, France, Spain,</hi> and of <hi>Illyricum</hi> had confirmed it; not that the confirmation and conſent demanded by General Councils of Great Sees, beſides that of <hi>Rome,</hi> did infer that the Councils did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon theſe Sees, as all men do agree. Nor can you infer, That the Councils did depend upon the Pope, upon pretence that they demanded his conſent and confirmation to their Decrees.</p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:44415:23"/>
                  <p>You may add to this, That Superiors have many times deſired their Inferiors to confirm their Acts; The Council of <hi>Sardica</hi> deſired all the Churches to whom they ſend their Synodal Epiſtle, That they would confirm what they had Decreed. The <hi>15th</hi> Council of <hi>Toledo</hi> confirmed the Decrees of the <hi>6th</hi> General Council, at the requeſt of <hi>Leo</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Conc. Toled. cap. 2. lib. 1.</note> the 2d. <hi>Pelagius</hi> the firſt deſired his Clergy to confirm his demand concerning Ordinations. <hi>Julian,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cales,</hi> the Popes Legate at the Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> ſays, in his Letters to the Emperor <hi>Leon,</hi> That this Prince had commanded all Bps that they ſhould confirm the Doctrine; of the Holy Apoſtles; and in the year 465, the Prelates of the <hi>3d</hi> Province of <hi>Lyons,</hi> being Aſſembled at <hi>Rennes,</hi> under <hi>Perpetuus</hi> Merropolitan of <hi>Tours,</hi> ſent their Decrets to <hi>Victorius</hi> and <hi>Thalaſſius</hi> of <hi>Angiers,</hi> who were not preſent, that by their Authorites they might confirm them; which clearly proves, that the confirmation of the Decrees of Councils by the Popes, is not a mark of the Popes ſuperiority over Councils. Now for the quality of Head, which was given to the Pope in the Councils of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> as you have obſerved, beſides that they were his own Legates that gave him this Title in the Council of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Act 2. and that St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and <hi>Juvenal</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> preſiding, the Council ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently ſhewed that they did not own the Pope as the Soveraign Head of the Church; I ſay, that this quality of Head carried with it no prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of Magiſtracy and of Dominion, but only a preheminence of Order, of Direction, and of Excellence. And it is in this ſenſe that <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> ſaid in the ſecond General Council, That by the death of <hi>Meleti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> the Council had loſt its Head; and there is nothing more ordinary a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Authors, whether they treat of Politick or Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, than to give the Title of Head and Chief to them who preſide in Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. It is in this ſenſe that the Fathers of the Council of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> give Pope <hi>Leo,</hi> who there preſided in the perſon of his Legates, the name of Head of this Council, according to the Order of the Emperor <hi>Martianus.</hi> Beſides, if the Title of Head, in matters of Faith and of Religion, hath been given to ſome Prelates, as to <hi>Nicephorus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to the Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> to St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> to St. <hi>Baſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> to <hi>Nicetius</hi> Bp of <hi>Treves,</hi> to <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Tours,</hi> and ſome others, by reaſon of the Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of their Sees, or becauſe of their Learning, of their Piety, and of their good Conduct; With how much more juſtice may the Bp of <hi>Rome</hi> have been honoured with it, he who was, not only the Metropolitan of ſome Bps, or the Exarch of a Dioceſs compoſed of Ten Provinces, but who, to ſpeak with<note n="*" place="margin">Epiſt. 52.</note> 
                     <hi>Theodorus Studita,</hi> was the firſt of the whole Body of the Church, and who occupied the firſt See of all Chriſtendom, and the See which was eſteemed the moſt eminent, either becauſe it had been oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied by St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> two the moſt famous of the Apoſtles, the firſt of which is called, even by the Holy Fathers, the Prince of the Society of the Apoſtles; or becauſe it was eſtabliſhed in a City, wherein reſided the Majeſty of the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and which was the Capital City of the World?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I am fully ſatisfied, and thank you for the kindne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s you have ſhewed in diſcourſing with me ſo long upon this matter, I now perceive the Truth and the importance of it; and I profeſs my ſelf, without more ado, to be of your opinion; but it is time for us to think of retiring.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:44415:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
